I really am honored to be here, and as Chris said,
كلي فخر بأن أكون هنا، كما قال كريس،
it's been over 20 years since I started working in Africa.
لقد مرت أكثر من 20 سنة منذ بدأت العمل في أفريقيا.
My first introduction was at the Abidjan airport on a sweaty, Ivory Coast morning.
أول قدومي كان في مطار ابيدجان في صباح جميل في ساحل العاج.
I had just left Wall Street, cut my hair to look like Margaret Mead,
كنت قد تركت وول أستريت للتو، وقصصت شعري لأبدو مثل مارغريت ميد،
given away most everything that I owned,
بترك كل شئ أملكه تقريباً،
and arrived with all the essentials --
ووصلت مع كل الضروريات--
some poetry, a few clothes, and, of course, a guitar --
بعض القصائد، قليل من الملابس، وبالطبع، الجيتار--
because I was going to save the world,
لأنني كنت ذاهبة لأنقذ العالم،
and I thought I would just start with the African continent.
وقد فكرت بأنني سأبدأ من القارة الأفريقية.
But literally within days of arriving I was told, in no uncertain terms,
لكن أخبروني حرفياً خلال أيام منذ وصولي، بعبارات لا لبس فيها ،
by a number of West African women, that Africans didn't want saving,
من قبل عدد من نساء غرب أفريقيا، أن الأفارقة لا يحتاجون لإنقاذ،
thank you very much, least of all not by me.
شكراً جزيلاً لك، على الأقل لن أنقذها أنا.
I was too young, unmarried, I had no children,
كنت يافعة جداً، ولست متزوجة، وليس لدي أطفال،
didn't really know Africa, and besides, my French was pitiful.
لم أكن أعرف أفريقيا وبجانب ذلك، كانت لغتي الفرنسية بائسة.
And so, it was an incredibly painful time in my life,
ولذا، لقد كان وقتاً مؤلماً بصورة لا تصدق في حياتي،
and yet it really started to give me the humility to start listening.
ولكن علمني حقاً التواضع لبدء الاستماع.
I think that failure can be an incredibly motivating force as well,
أعتقد أن الفشل أيضاً يمكن أن يكون قوى دافعة بصورة لا تصدق،
so I moved to Kenya and worked in Uganda,
لذا إنتقلت إلى كينيا وعملت في يوغندا،
and I met a group of Rwandan women, who asked me, in 1986,
وإلتقيت بمجموعة من النساء الروانديات، اللاتي طلبوا مني ، عام 1986،
to move to Kigali to help them start the first microfinance institution there.
للإنتقال إلى كيغالي لمساعدتهم في بداية أول مؤسسة تمويل مشاريع إقتصادية صغيرة هناك.
And I did, and we ended up naming it Duterimbere,
وقد فعلت، وقد أنتهى بنا الحال بتسميته Duterimbere ،
meaning "to go forward with enthusiasm." And while we were doing it,
وتعني" تمضي إلى الأمام مع الحماس." وبينما كنا نشيّده،
I realized that there weren't a lot of businesses that were viable
أدركت أنه لم تكن هناك الكثير من الشركات التي كانت قابلة للحياة
and started by women, and so maybe I should try to run a business, too.
وقد بدأت بالنساء، ولذا ربما عليّ أن أحاول بدء أعمال أيضاً.
And so I started looking around, and I heard about a bakery
ولذا بدأت بالنظر في الجوار، وسمعت الكثير حول المخابز
that was run by 20 prostitutes.
الذي كانت تديره 20 غانية.
And, being a little intrigued, I went to go meet this group,
وكوني مفتونة قليلاً، ذهبت للقاء هذه المجموعة،
and what I found was 20 unwed mothers who were trying to survive.
وما وجدته كان 20 أم غير متزوجة اللاتي يحاولن البقاء على قيد الحياة.
And it was really the beginning of my understanding the power of language,
وقد كانت حقاً بداية فهمي لسلطة اللغة،
and how what we call people so often distances us from them,
وكيف أن ما نطلقه في الغالب على الناس البعيدين منا،
and makes them little.
وجعلهم صغار.
I also found out that the bakery was nothing like a business,
وقد عرفت أيضاً أن المخبز لم يكن أي شئ يشبه الأعمال،
that, in fact, it was a classic charity run by a well-intentioned person,
في الواقع، لقد كان عملاً خيرياً كلاسيكياً يديره شخص حسن النية
who essentially spent 600 dollars a month
الذي كان في الأساس يصرف 600 دولار شهرياً
to keep these 20 women busy making little crafts and baked goods,
لجعل تلك النسوة مشغولين بصنع المنسوجات الصغيرة وتغليف السلع،
and living on 50 cents a day, still in poverty.
ويعيشون على 50 سنتاً يومياً، ومازالوا فقراء.
So, I made a deal with the women. I said, "Look, we get rid of the charity side,
لذا، عقدت إتفاقاً مع النساء. قلت، " أنظروا، يجب أن نتخلص من جانب المؤسسة الخيرية،
and we run this as a business and I'll help you."
ونشغّل هذا كعمل تجاري وسأساعدكم."
They nervously agreed. I nervously started, and, of course,
لقد وافقوا بتوتّر، وبدأت بتوتّر، وبالطبع،
things are always harder than you think they're going to be.
الأشياء دائماً أصعب مما نتخيل أنها ستكون.
First of all, I thought, well, we need a sales team,
بادئ ذي بدء، فكرت، حسناً نحتاج لفريق مبيعات،
and we clearly aren't the A-Team here,
وكان من الواضح أننا لسنا الفريق هنا،
so let's -- I did all this training.
لذا دعونا -- قمت بكل هذا التدريب،
And the epitome was when I literally marched into the streets
وكان يضرب به المثل عندما ذهبت حرفيا الى شوارع
of Nyamirambo, which is the popular quarter of Kigali, with a bucket,
نياميرامبو، التي هي الجزء الأشهر في كيغالي، أحمل الدلو،
and I sold all these little doughnuts to people,
وقمت ببيع كل هذه الخبائز الصغيرة للناس،
and I came back, and I was like, "You see?"
وعدت أدراجي، وكنت أقول، " هل رأيتن؟"
And the women said, "You know, Jacqueline, who in Nyamirambo is not going to buy
وتقول النسوة، " تعرفي، جاكلين، سكان نياميرامبو لن يشتروا
doughnuts out of an orange bucket from a tall American woman?" And like --
الخبائز من الدلو البرتغالي من إمرأة أمريكية طويلة؟" ومثل --
(Laughter) -- it's a good point.
(ضحك) إنها نقطة جيدة.
So then I went the whole American way,
عندئذ ذهبت بنفس الطريق الأمريكي،
with competitions, team and individual. Completely failed,
مع المنافسة، الفريق و الفرد. فشلت تماماً،
but over time, the women learnt to sell on their own way.
لكن عبر الزمن تعلمت النسوة البيع على طريقتهن الخاصة.
And they started listening to the marketplace,
وقد بدأوا في الإستماع لعالم التجارة،
and they came back with ideas for cassava chips, and banana chips,
وقد عادوا بأفكار لرقائق الكسافا ورقائق الموز
and sorghum bread, and before you knew it,
وخبز الذرة ، وقبل أن تعرفوها،
we had cornered the Kigali market,
قمنا بالهيمنة على سوق كيغالي،
and the women were earning three to four times the national average.
وكانت النسوة يكسبن ثلاثة إلى أربعة أضعاف متوسط الدخل في الدولة.
And with that confidence surge, I thought, "Well, it's time to create a real bakery,
ومع إرتفاع تلك الثقة، فكرت، حسناً، إنه الوقت لإقامة مخبز حقيقي،
so let's paint it." And the women said, "That's a really great idea."
لذا فلنقم بطلائه. وقالت النساء، " تلك حقاً فكرة عظيمة."
And I said, "Well, what color do you want to paint it?" And they said,
وقلت، " حسناً، ما هو اللون الذي تريدون طلائه؟" وقد قالوا،
"Well, you choose." And I said, "No, no, I'm learning to listen.
"حسناً، أنت تختاري." فقلت، " لا، لا، أنا أتعلم الإستماع --
You choose. It's your bakery, your street, your country -- not mine."
أنتن تختاروا. إنه مخبزكم، شارعكم، بلدكم، ليست بلدي."
But they wouldn't give me an answer.
لكنهم لا يعطوني أي إجابة.
So, one week, two weeks, three weeks went by,
لذا، مرّ أسبوع، أسبوعين، ثلاثة أسابيع،
and finally I said, "Well, how about blue?"
وفي النهاية، قلت" حسناً، ما رأيكم باللون الأزرق؟"
And they said, "Blue, blue, we love blue. Let's do it blue."
فقالوا ، " أزرق، أزرق، نحن نحب الأزرق. لنطليه باللون الأزرق."
So, I went to the store, I brought Gaudence, the recalcitrant one of all,
لذا، فقد ذهبت إلى المتجر، وجلبت غاودنس ، المتمردة على كل شئ،
and we brought all this paint and fabric to make curtains,
وقد جلبنا كل هذا الطلاء والقماش لصنع الستائر،
and on painting day, we all gathered in Nyamirambo,
وفي يوم الطلاء إجتمعنا كلنا في نياميرامبو ،
and the idea was we would paint it white with blue as trim,
وكانت الفكرة هي أننا سنطليه بالأبيض مع الأزرق كتقليمة،
like a little French bakery. But that was clearly not as satisfying
مثل المخبز الفرنسي الصغير. لكن كان واضحاً أن ذلك لم يكن مرضياً
as painting a wall of blue like a morning sky.
كطلاء الحائط باللون الأزرق مثل سماء الصباح.
So, blue, blue, everything became blue.
إذاً، أزرق، أزرق، أصبح كل شئ أزرق.
The walls were blue, the windows were blue,
كانت الحوائط زرقاء، النوافذ زرقاء،
the sidewalk out front was painted blue.
وتم طلاء الممشى أمام المخبز باللون الأزرق.
And Aretha Franklin was shouting "R-E-S-P-E-C-T,"
وكانت أريثا فرانكلين تصرخ " ريسبكت،"
the women's hips were swaying
وكانت أوراك النسوة تتمايل
and little kids were trying to grab the paintbrushes, but it was their day.
ويحاول الأطفال الصغر سحب فرشة الطلاء، لكنه كان يومهم.
And at the end of it, we stood across the street
وفي نهاية اليوم، وقفنا عبر الطريق
and we looked at what we had done, and I said, "It is so beautiful."
ونظرنا إلى ما قمنا بإنجازه، وقلت، " إنه جميل حقاً،"
And the women said, "It really is."
وقالت النسوة، " إنه حقاً جميل."
And I said, "And I think the color is perfect,"
وقلت، " وأعتقد أن اللون ممتاز،"
and they all nodded their head, except for Gaudence,
وقد أومأوا برؤوسهن موافقةً ، باستثناء غاودنس،
and I said, "What?"
وقد قلت، " ماذا؟"
And she said, "Nothing." And I said, "What?"
وقد قالت، " لا شئ،" وقلت، " ماذا؟"
And she said, "Well, it is pretty, but, you know, our color, really, it is green." And --
وقد قالت، " حسناً، إنه جميل، لكنك تعرفي أن لوننا حقاً هو الاخضر." و--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- I learned then that listening isn't just about patience,
وقد تعلمت حينها أن الإستماع ليس فقط حول الصبر،
but that when you've lived on charity and dependent your whole life long,
لكن عندما تعيش طوال حياتك معتمد على الإعانات،
it's really hard to say what you mean.
من الصعب حقاً أن تقول ما تعنيه.
And, mostly because people never really ask you,
و غالباً لأن الناس لا يطلبون منك بتاتاً،
and when they do, you don't really think they want to know the truth.
وحينما يطلبون، فأنت لا تعتقد مطلقاً أنهم يرغبون بمعرفة الحقيقة.
And so then I learned that listening is not only about waiting,
ولذا فقد تعلمت أن الإستماع ليس فقط متعلق بالإنتظار،
but it's also learning how better to ask questions.
لكنه أيضاً تعلم كيف تطرح الأسئلة بصورة أفضل.
And so, I lived in Kigali for about two and a half years, doing these two things,
ولذا، فقد عشت في كيغالي حوالي سنتين ونصف، أفعل هذين الشيئين،
and it was an extraordinary time in my life.
وقد كانت أوقاتاً غير إعتيادية في حياتي.
And it taught me three lessons
وقد علمتني ثلاث دروس
that I think are so important for us today,
وأعتقد أنها مهمة جداً بالنسبة لنا اليوم،
and certainly in the work that I do.
وبالتأكيد في العمل الذي أقوم به.
The first is that dignity is more important to the human spirit than wealth.
الأول هو أن الكرامة أكثر أهميةً للنفس البشرية من الثروة.
As Eleni has said, when people gain income, they gain choice,
وكما قالت إليني، حينما يكسب الناس دخلاً أكثر، يكتسبون الخيار،
and that is fundamental to dignity.
وذلك أساسي للكرامة.
But as human beings, we also want to see each other,
لكننا كبشر نرغب كذلك في رؤية بعضنا البعض،
and we want to be heard by each other, and we should never forget that.
ونرغب في أن نُسمع من قبل بعضنا البعض، ولا ينبغي نسيان ذلك مطلقاً.
The second is that traditional charity and aid
الدرس الثاني هو أن الأعمال الخيرية التقليدية والمساعدات
are never going to solve the problems of poverty.
لن تحلّ مشاكل الفقر مطلقاً.
I think Andrew pretty well covered that, so I will move to the third point,
وأعتقد أن أندرو قام بتغطية ذلك بصورة جيدة، لذا سأنتقل للدرس الثالث،
which is that markets alone also
التي هي أن ترك الأسواق لوحدها أيضاً
are not going to solve the problems of poverty.
لن يقوم بحل مشاكل الفقر.
Yes, we ran this as a business,
نعم، نحن نشغّل هذا كعمل تجاري،
but someone needed to pay the philanthropic support
لكن يحتاج لشخص ما لدفع دعم للاعمال الخيرية
that came into the training, and the management support, the strategic advice
التي جاءت لدعم التدريب والإدارة، والإستشارة الإستراتيجية
and, maybe most important of all,
وربما الأكثر أهمية عن كل شئ،
the access to new contacts, networks and new markets.
توفير إتصالات بأناس جُدد، شبكات وأسواق جديدة.
And so, on a micro level, there's a real role for this combination
ولذا، على المستوى الجزئي، هناك دور حقيقي لهذا الجمع
of investment and philanthropy.
بين الإستثمار والعمل الخيري.
And on a macro level -- some of the speakers have inferred that
وعلى المستوى الجزئي، بعض المتحدثين قد نفذوا إلى أنه
even health should be privatized.
حتى القطاع الصحي يجب أن يتم خصخصته.
But, having had a father with heart disease,
لكن، لأن والدي كان مصاباً بمرض القلب،
and realizing that what our family could afford
وأنني مدركة لما تستطيع أسرتنا توفيره
was not what he should have gotten,
لم يكن هو ما ينبغي أن يتلقاه،
and having a good friend step in to help,
وبعد خطوة صديق حميم للمساعدة،
I really believe that all people deserve access to health
أعتقد حقاً أن جميع الناس يستحقون الحصول على رعاية صحية
at prices they can afford.
بالكلفة التي يستطيعون دفعها.
I think the market can help us figure that out,
وأعتقد أن السوق يمكن أن يساعدنا في معرفة ذلك،
but there's got to be a charitable component,
لكن ينبغي أن يحتوي على عنصر عمل خيري
or I don't think we're going to create the kind of societies we want to live in.
أو لا أعتقد أننا سننشئ ذلك النوع من المجتمعات التي نرغب بالعيش بها.
And so, it was really those lessons that made me decide to
ولذا، كانت تلك حقاً الدروس التي جعلتني أقرر
build Acumen Fund about six years ago.
إنشاء أكيومن للتمويل قبل حوالي ست سنوات.
It's a nonprofit, venture capital fund for the poor,
إنها مؤسسة غير ربحية لتمويل الفقراء،
a few oxymorons in one sentence.
يبدو الامر متناقض قليلاً في الجملة السابقة .. ولكي أوضح
It essentially raises charitable funds from individuals, foundations and corporations,
فإنها تقوم في الأساس بإنشاء صناديق خيرية من الأفراد، المؤسسات والشركات،
and then we turn around and we invest equity and loans
ثم نتنقل في المكان ونستثمر الأسهم والقروض
in both for-profit and nonprofit entities
في كل من الأجسام الغير ربحية والربحية
that deliver affordable health, housing, energy, clean water
التي تقدم رعاية صحية بكلفة منخفضة، الإسكان، الطاقة، المياة النظيفة،
to low income people in South Asia and Africa,
للناس ذوي الدخول المنخفضة في جنوب آسيا وأفريقيا،
so that they can make their own choices.
بحيث يستطيعون إتخاذ قرارتهم الخاصة.
We've invested about 20 million dollars in 20 different enterprises,
نحن نستثمر حوالي 20 مليون دولار في 20 مؤسسة مختلفة،
and have, in so doing, created nearly 20,000 jobs,
وقد صنعنا بفعلنا هذا قرابة ال 20،000 وظيفة،
and delivered tens of millions of services to people
وقدمنا مئات الملايين من الخدمات للناس
who otherwise would not be able to afford them.
الذين لن يستطيعوا توفيرها بأي طريقة أخرى.
I want to tell you two stories. Both of them are in Africa.
سأسرد عليكم قصتين. كلا القصتين من أفريقيا.
Both of them are about investing in entrepreneurs
كلاهما حول الإستثمار في رجال الأعمال
who are committed to service, and who really know the markets.
الضالعين في الخدمات، الذين يعرفون السوق حقاً.
Both of them live at the confluence of public health and enterprise,
كلاهما تعيش في مقرن الرعاية الصحية والمؤسسات،
and both of them, because they're manufacturers,
وكلاهما، لأنهما مصنّعين،
create jobs directly, and create incomes indirectly,
يخلقون الوظائف مباشرة، ويجنون الدخل بصورة غير مباشرة،
because they're in the malaria sector,
لأنهما في قطاع الملاريا،
and Africa loses about 13 billion dollars a year because of malaria.
وتفقد أفريقيا حوالي 13 مليار دولار سنوياً بسبب الملاريا.
And so as people get healthier, they also get wealthier.
ولذا فكلما أصبح الناس أكثر صحةً، يصبحون أيضاً أكثر ثراءً.
The first one is called Advanced Bio-Extracts Limited.
الأولى تسمى Advanced Bio-Extracts Limited.
It's a company built in Kenya about seven years ago
وهي شركة تأسست في كينيا قبل حوالي سبع سنوات
by an incredible entrepreneur named Patrick Henfrey and his three colleagues.
بواسطة رجل أعمال مذهل يسمى باتريك هينفري وثلاثة من زملائه.
These are old-hand farmers
هؤلاء المزارعون القدامى
who've gone through all the agricultural ups and downs
قد مروا بكل صعود وهبوط الزراعة
in Kenya over the last 30 years.
في كينيا خلال ال 30 سنة الماضية.
Now, this plant is an Artemisia plant;
، وهذا المصنع هو مصنع عقار الأرطماسيا
it's the basic component for artemisinin,
وهو العنصر الأساسي لتلك المشتقات ،
which is the best-known treatment for malaria.
الذي هو أفضل علاج معروف للملاريا.
It's indigenous to China and the Far East,
إن موطنه الأصل هو الصين والشرق الأقصى،
but given that the prevalence of malaria is here in Africa,
ولكن بالنظر إلى أن معدل انتشار الملاريا هنا في افريقيا ،
Patrick and his colleagues said, "Let's bring it here,
قال باتريك وزملائه، " لنجلبه هنا،
because it's a high value-add product."
لأنه منتج ذا قيمة مضافة مرتفعة."
The farmers get three to four times the yields that they would with maize.
يحصل المزارعون على ثلاثة إلى أربعة أضعاف غلة الذرة.
And so, using patient capital -- money that they could raise early on,
ولذا، بإستخدام رأس المال الصبور، المال الذي يستطيعون جنيّه مبكراً،
that actually got below market returns
الذي يصبح أقل من عائد السوق،
and was willing to go the long haul and be combined
كان على استعداد للذهاب لمسافات طويلة ويتم جمعه
with management assistance, strategic assistance --
مع مساعدة إدارية، ومساعدة إستراتيجية،
they've now created a company where they purchase from 7,500 farmers.
ولقد اقاموا شركة الآن حيث يشترون من 7500 مزارعاً.
So that's about 50,000 people affected.
ولذا فأن 50000 شخص قد تأثروا.
And I think some of you may have visited --
وأعتقد أن بعضكم ربما زار --
these farmers are helped by KickStart and TechnoServe,
هؤلاء المزراعين تمت مساعدتهم من قبل KickStart و TechnoServe،
who help them become more self-sufficient.
الذين ساعدوهم ليصبحوا أكثر كفاءةً ذاتياً.
They buy it, they dry it and they bring it to this factory,
إنهم يشترونها، يجففونها ويجلبوها إلى المصنع
which was purchased in part by, again, patient capital from Novartis,
الذي تم شراؤها جزئياً بواسطة رأس المال الصبور مجدداً من نوفارتيس ،
who has a real interest in getting the powder
الذي لديه إهتمام حقيقي بالحصول على المسحوق
so that they can make Coartem.
بحيث يمكنهم صنع عقار كوارتيم.
Acumen's been working with ABE for the past year, year and a half,
كانت أكيوم تعمل مع ABE خلال العام المنصرم، عام ونصف،
both on looking at a new business plan,
كلاهما يتطلعان لخطة أعمال جديدة،
and what does expansion look like, helping with management support
وما يبدو عليه التوسع، المساعدة عبر الدعم الإداري
and helping to do term sheets and raise capital.
والمساعدة في صياغة الأوراق وتوفير رأس المال.
And I really understood what patient capital meant emotionally
وقد أستوعبت حقاً ما يعنيه رأس المال الصبور عاطفياً
in the last month or so. Because the company was literally
في الشهر الماضي أو هكذا. لأن الشركة كانت حرفياً
10 days away from proving that the product they produced
بعيدة 10 أيام من إثبات أن المنتج الذي ينتجونه
was at the world-quality level needed to make Coartem,
كان على مستوى الجودة العالمية اللازمة لصنع عقار كوارتيم،
when they were in the biggest cash crisis of their history.
بينما كانوا في أكبر أزمة سيولة خلال تاريخهم.
And we called all of the social investors we know.
وقد أتصلنا بمستثمرينا الإجتماعيين الذين نعرفهم.
Now, some of these same social investors are really interested in Africa
وبعض أؤلئك هم نفس المستثمرون الإجتماعيون الذين يهتمون حقاً بأفريقيا
and understand the importance of agriculture,
ويفهمون أهمية الزراعة،
and they even helped the farmers.
وقد ساعدوا حتى المزارعين.
And even when we explained that if ABE goes away,
وحتى عندما أوضحنا أنه إن ذهبت ABE ،
all those 7,500 jobs go away too,
فكل ال 7500 وظيفة أيضاً ستذهب،
we sometimes have this bifurcation between business and the social.
بعض الأحيان لدينا هذا التشعب بين الأعمال والإجتماعيات.
And it's really time we start thinking more creatively about how they can be fused.
وإنه لحقاً الوقت لبداية التفكير بإبتكار أكثر حول الكيفية التي يمزجان بها.
So Acumen made not one, but two bridge loans,
إذاً فقد قامت أكيوم بتيسير قرضين بدلاً عن واحد،
and the good news is they did indeed meet world-quality classification and are now
والشئ المفرح هو أنهم بالفعل وصلوا لتصنيف الجودة العالمية وهم الآن
in the final stages of closing a 20-million-dollar round, to move it to the next level,
في المراحل النهائية لإكمال جولة 20 مليون دولار للإنتقال للمرحلة التالية
and I think that this will be one of the more important companies in East Africa.
وأعتقد أن هذه ستكون أحد أهم الشركات في شرق أفريقيا.
This is Samuel. He's a farmer.
هذا هو صامويل. إنه مزارع.
He was actually living in the Kibera slums
لقد كان يعيش في أحياء كيبيرا الفقيرة
when his father called him and told him about Artemisia and the value-add potential.
عندما أستدعاه والده وأخبره عن الأرطماسيا والقيمة المضافة المحتملة.
So he moved back to the farm, and, long story short,
لذا فقد أنتقل مجدداً إلى المزرعة، ولإختصار القصة الطويلة،
they now have seven acres under cultivation.
فان لديهم الآن سبعة فدانات مزروعة.
Samuel's kids are in private school,
أطفال صامويل في مدرسة خاصة،
and he's starting to help other farmers in the area also go into Artemisia production --
وقد بدأ بمساعدة مزارعين آخرين في المنطقة أيضاً ليدخلوا في إنتاج الأرطماسيا--
dignity being more important than wealth.
الكرامة أهم بكثير من الثروة.
The next one, many of you know.
القصة الثانية، يعرفها الكثيرون منكم.
I talked about it a little at Oxford two years ago,
لقد تحدثت قليلاً في أوكسفورد قبل عامين،
and some of you visited A to Z manufacturing,
وقد زار بعضكم مصانع A to Z،
which is one of the great, real companies in East Africa.
التي هي أحدى الشركات العظيمة في شرق أفريقيا.
It's another one that lives at the confluence of health and enterprise.
إنه شركة أخرى تعمل في مقرن الصحة والشركة.
And this is really a story about a public-private solution
وهذه حقاً قصة حول الحلول العامة/الخاصة
that has really worked.
التي نجحت بالفعل.
It started in Japan. Sumitomo had developed a technology
لقد بدأت في اليابان. طورت سوميتومو تكنلوجيا
essentially to impregnate a polyethylene-based fiber with organic insecticide,
أساسا لتلقيح التكنولوجيا من ألياف البولي ايثيلين - مع المبيدات الحشرية العضوية ،
so you could create a bed net,
بحيث يمكنك صنع الناموسية،
a malaria bed net, that would last five years and not need to be re-dipped.
ناموسية للوقاية من الملاريا تعيش خمسة سنوات ولا تحتاج لإعادة معالجة.
It could alter the vector, but like Artemisia,
ويمكن أن تغيّر الحشرة الناقلة ، ولكن مثل الأرطماسيا ،
it had been produced only in East Asia. And as part of its social responsibility,
تم إنتاجها فقط في شرق آسيا، كجزء من مسؤوليتها الإجتماعية
Sumitomo said, "Why don't we experiment
قال سوميتومو، " لم لا نجرب
with whether we can produce it in Africa, for Africans?"
سواء كنّا نستطيع إنتاجها في افريقيا، للأفارقة؟"
UNICEF came forward and said, "We'll buy most of the nets,
تقدمت اليونيسف وقالت، " سنشتري معظم هذه الناموسيات
and then we'll give them away, as part of the global fund's
ثم نقدمها كجزء من المساعدات الدولية
and the U.N.'s commitment to pregnant women and children, for free."
وإلتزام الأمم المتحدة تجاه النساء الحوامل والأطفال، مجاناً."
Acumen came in with the patient capital,
جاءت أكيومن برأس المال الصبور،
and we also helped to identify the entrepreneur
وقد ساعدنا أيضاً في تحديد الأعمال
that we would all partner with here in Africa,
التي ينبغي المشاركة معها هنا في أفريقيا،
and Exxon provided the initial resin.
وقدمت Exxon مادة الراتنج المبدئية.
Well, in looking around for entrepreneurs,
حسناً بالنظر في الجوار على الأعمال،
there was none better that we could find on earth than Anuj Shah,
لم يكن هناك شخص يمكن إيجاده على الأرض أفضل من أنوج شاه،
in A to Z manufacturing company.
في شركة A to Z للتصنيع.
It's a 40-year-old company, it understands manufacturing.
إنها شركة عمرها 40 عاماً، وتفهم في التصنيع.
It's gone from socialist Tanzania into capitalist Tanzania,
لقد تحولت من تنزانيا الإشتراكية إلى تنزانيا الرأسمالية،
and continued to flourish. It had about 1,000 employees when we first found it.
وواصلت في الإزدهار. ولديها حوالي 1000 موظف حينما وجدناها في البداية.
And so, Anuj took the entrepreneurial risk here in Africa
ولذا، أخذت أنوج مخاطر الأعمال هنا في أفريقيا
to produce a public good that was purchased by the aid establishment
لإنتاج سلع عامة كانت تم شراؤها بواسطة مؤسسة مساعدات
to work with malaria.
للعمل في الملاريا.
And, long story short, again, they've been so successful.
ولإختصار القصة الطويلة مجدداً، لقد كانوا ناجحين بشدة.
In our first year, the first net went off the line in October of 2003.
في أول سنة لنا، أول ناموسية انتجت في أكتوبر 2003.
We thought the hitting-it-out-of-the-box number was 150,000 nets a year.
فكرنا بأن الرقم المطلوب للإنتاج كان 150000 ناموسية سنوياً.
This year, they are now producing eight million nets a year,
هذه السنة يقومون بانتاج ثماني ملايين ناموسية سنوياً،
and they employ 5,000 people, 90 percent of whom are women, mostly unskilled.
ويوظفون 5000 شخص، 90 بالمائة منهم نساء، غالباً ليس لديهن مهارات.
They're in a joint venture with Sumitomo.
وهم الآن في شراكة مع سوميتومو.
And so, from an enterprise perspective for Africa,
ولذا، من وجهة نظر شركات لأفريقيا،
and from a public health perspective, these are real successes.
ومن وجهة نظر الرعاية الصحية، فهذه نجاحات حقيقية.
But it's only half the story if we're really looking at solving problems of poverty,
لكنها فقط نصف القصة إذا كنا نتطلع لحل مشاكل الفقر،
because it's not long-term sustainable.
لأنه ليس مستدماً على المدى البعيد.
It's a company with one big customer.
إنها شركة ذات زبون واحد ضخم.
And if avian flu hits, or for any other reason
وإذا أنتشر وباء أنفلونزا الطيور، أو لأي سبب آخر
the world decides that malaria is no longer as much of a priority, everybody loses.
قرر العالم أن الملاريا لم تعد أولوية قصوى، فسيخسر الجميع.
And so, Anuj and Acumen
ولذا، كانت أنجوج وأكيومن
have been talking about testing the private sector,
يتحدثان عن إختبار القطاع الخاص،
because the assumption that the aid establishment has made is that,
لأن الفرضية بأن تأسيس المساعدات قد أوصلها إلى هناك،
look, in a country like Tanzania,
أنظروا في بلد مثل تنزانيا،
80 percent of the population makes less than two dollars a day.
80 بالمائة من السكان يجنون أقل من دولارين يومياً.
It costs, at manufacturing point, six dollars to produce these,
إنها تكلف في نقطة الإنتاج، ست دولارات لإنتاج تلك،
and it costs the establishment another six dollars to distribute it,
وتكلف المؤسس ست دولارات أخرى لتوزيعها،
so the market price in a free market would be about 12 dollars per net.
لذا فسعر السوق في السوق المفتوح سيكون حوالي 12 دولار للناموسية.
Most people can't afford that, so let's give it away free.
لا يستطيع معظم الناس توفير كلفتها، لذا لنقم بتقديمها مجاناً.
And we said, "Well, there's another option.
وقلنا، " حسناً، هناك خيار آخر.
Let's use the market as the best listening device we have, and
لنستخدم السوق كأفضل أداة للتتحسس لدينا ، و
understand at what price people would pay for this, so they get the dignity of choice.
نفهم بأي سعر سيدفع الناس، بحيث يحصلون على كرامة الإختيار.
We can start building local distribution,
يمكننا البدء بتأسيس موزعين محليين،
and actually, it can cost the public sector much less."
وفي الواقع، يمكن أن تكلف القطاع العام أقل بكثير."
And so we came in with a second round of patient capital to A to Z,
ولذا فقد توصلنا لنموذج ثاني لرأس المال الصبور ل A to Z،
a loan as well as a grant, so that A to Z could play with pricing
قرض وكذلك منحة، بحيث تستطيع A to Z اللعب بالأسعار
and listen to the marketplace, and found a number of things.
وتتحسس السوق، ووجدنا عدد من الأشياء.
One, that people will pay different prices,
أولاً، أن الناس سوف تدفع أسعار مختلفة،
but the overwhelming number of people will come forth at one dollar per net
لكن أعداد مأهولة من الناس ستأتي للشراء بدولار واحد للناموسية
and make a decision to buy it.
وسوف يتخذون قراراً بشرائها.
And when you listen to them, they'll also have a lot to say
وعندما تستمع إليهم، فان لديهم أيضاً الكثير ليقولونه
about what they like and what they don't like.
حول ما أعجبهم وما لم يعجبهم،
And that some of the channels we thought would work didn't work.
وأن بعض القنوات التي أعتقدنا أنها ستنجح لم تنجح.
But because of this experimentation and iteration that was allowed
لكن بسبب هذه التجربة والتعديلات المسموح بها
because of the patient capital,
بفضل رأس المال الصبور،
we've now found that it costs about a dollar in the private sector
لقد قمنا الآن بالوصول إلى أنها تكلف حوالي دولار في القطاع الخاص
to distribute, and a dollar to buy the net.
لتوزيعها، ودولار لشراء الناموسية.
So then, from a policy perspective, when you start with the market,
لذا، من وجهة نظر السياسات، عندما تبدأ مع السوق،
we have a choice.
فلدينا خيار.
We can continue going along at 12 dollars a net, and the customer pays zero,
يمكننا الإستمرار بناموسية تكلف 12 دولاراً، ولا يدفع الزبائن شيئاً،
or we could at least experiment with some of it, to charge one dollar a net,
أو يمكننا على الأقل تجربة بعض منها وأن يدفعوا دولاراً للناموسية،
costing the public sector another six dollars a net,
مكلفةً القطاع العام ست دولارات أخرى للناموسية،
give the people the dignity of choice, and have a distribution system
أعط الناس كرامة الإختيار، وتوفير نظام توزيع
that might, over time, start sustaining itself.
الذي ربما عبر الزمن، يبدأ بإستدامة نفسه.
We've got to start having conversations like this,
بدأنا في مناقشات مثل هذه،
and I don't think there's any better way to start than using the market,
ولا أعتقد أن هناك طريقة أفضل للبدء من إستخدام السوق،
but also to bring other people to the table around it.
لكن أيضاً لجمع الآخرين لمائدة حوار مستديرة.
Whenever I go to visit A to Z, I think of my grandmother, Stella.
كلما أذهب لزيارة A to Z، أفكر بجدتي، ستيلا.
She was very much like those women sitting behind the sewing machines.
لقد كانت لحد كبير تشبه أؤلئك النسوة الجالسات خلف ماكينات الخياطة.
She grew up on a farm in Austria, very poor,
لقد ترعرعت في مزرعة في النمسا، فقيرة جداً،
didn't have very much education.
لم تحصل على الكثير من التعليم.
She moved to the United States, where she met my grandfather,
لقد إنتقلت إلى الولايات المتحدة حيث ألتقت بجدي
who was a cement hauler,
الذي كان متعهد نقل الأسمنت،
and they had nine children. Three of them died as babies.
وأنجبوا تسعة أطفال. ثلاثة منهم ماتوا وهم أطفال.
My grandmother had tuberculosis, and she worked in a sewing machine shop,
أصيبت جدتي بالسُل، وكانت تعمل بمتجر ماكينات الخياطة
making shirts for about 10 cents an hour.
تصنع القمصان مقابل 10 سنتات للساعة.
She, like so many of the women I see at A to Z,
وهي مثل الكثير من النسوة اللاتي أراهم في A to Z،
worked hard every day, understood what suffering was,
عملت بجد يومياً، تفهم ما تعنيه المعاناة،
had a deep faith in God, loved her children
لديها إيمان قوي بالله، أحبت أطفالها
and would never have accepted a handout.
ولم تقبل مطلقاً بالإعانات.
But because she had the opportunity of the marketplace,
لكن لأنه توفرت لها فرصة السوق،
and she lived in a society that provided the safety
عاشت في المجتمع الذي يوفر الأمان
of having access to affordable health and education,
بالحصول على رعاية صحية وتعليم بأسعار في متناول اليد،
her children and their children were able to live
أستطاع أطفالها وأطفالهم العيش
lives of real purpose and follow real dreams.
حياة لهدف حقيقي وتحقيق أحلام حقيقية.
I look around at my siblings and my cousins -- and as I said,
أتأمل في أخواتي وأبناء عمومتي-- وكما قلت،
there are a lot of us --
هناك الكثير منا --
and I see teachers and musicians, hedge fund managers, designers.
وأرى المعلمين والموسيقيين، مدراء صندوق هيدج، المصممين.
One sister who makes other people's wishes come true.
أختي التي تجعل أحلام الآخرين تتحقق.
And my wish, when I see those women, I meet those farmers,
وأمنيتي، عندما أرى أؤلئك النسوة، والتقي بأؤلئك المزارعين،
and I think about all the people across this continent
وأفكر بكل أؤلئك الناس عبر هذه القارة
who are working hard every day,
الذين يعملون بجد يومياً،
is that they have that sense of opportunity and possibility,
وأن لديهم الإحساس بالفرصة والإمكانية،
and that they also can believe and get access to services,
وأنهم أيضاً يمكن أن يصدقوا ويحصلوا على الخدمات
so that their children, too, can live those lives of great purpose.
بحيث يستطيع أطفالهم أيضاً تلك الحياة لهدف عظيم.
It shouldn't be that difficult.
لا ينبغي أن أكون بتلك الصعوبة.
But what it takes is a commitment from all of us
لكن ما تحتاجه هو إلتزام منا جميعاً
to essentially refuse trite assumptions,
لأن نرفض بالأساس الإفتراضات المبتذلة،
get out of our ideological boxes.
والخروج من علبنا الإيديولوجية.
It takes investing in those entrepreneurs that are committed
إنها تتطلب أن نستثمر في رجال الأعمال الملتزمين
to service as well as to success.
بالخدمات وأيضاً بالنجاح.
It takes opening your arms, both, wide,
وتتطلب سواعدكم، كلاها، فسيحة،
and expecting very little love in return,
وأن تتوقع القليل من الحب بالمقابل،
but demanding accountability,
وبطلب المساءلة،
and bringing the accountability to the table as well.
وجلب المساءلة لهذه الطاولة أيضاً.
And most of all, most of all,
وفوق كل شئ، فوق كل شئ،
it requires that all of us have the courage and the patience,
إنها تتطلب منا جميعاً الشجاعة والصبر،
whether we are rich or poor, African or non-African,
سواء كنت غنياً أو فقيراً، أفريقي أو غير أفريقي،
local or diaspora, left or right,
تعيش هنا أو في الشتات، يسار أو يمين،
to really start listening to each other.
لنبدأ حقاً بالإستماع لبعضنا البعض.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)